<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>codessl.com</title><link>https://www.codessl.com/</link><description>Recent content on codessl.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 17:50:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.codessl.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What the F[_]? A quick introduction to Higher Kinded Types in Scala</title><link>https://www.codessl.com/posts/2021-12-29-what-the-f-higher-kinded-type/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 17:50:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.codessl.com/posts/2021-12-29-what-the-f-higher-kinded-type/</guid><description>Generics in Scala We can have generics in Scala through type constructors.
For example, we can have List[A] which is a type that accepts a type argument A such that A can be any types. Why do we need this? Well, this is so that we can write generic methods or functions as follows.
def doSomething[A](list: List[A], a: A): List[A] = ??? val newIntList: List[Int] = doSomething(List(1, 2, 3), 3) val newStringList: List[String] = doSomething(List(&amp;#34;alpha&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;beta&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;delta&amp;#34;), &amp;#34;omicron&amp;#34;) Note that doSomething works with List[Int] or List[String] or a List of anything for that matter.</description></item><item><title>A quick introduction to functional effects in Scala</title><link>https://www.codessl.com/posts/2021-12-26-a-quick-intro-to-functional-effects-scala/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 16:15:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://www.codessl.com/posts/2021-12-26-a-quick-intro-to-functional-effects-scala/</guid><description>What is an Effect and why do you need it? Functional programming (FP) is easy if you just have to write pure functions that do some calculation based on some inputs and return some output. However, most useful programs involve side effects, for instance querying a database system, calling an internal or external API, reading/writing files or even printing to console. The act of performing any of those side effects is considered an &amp;ldquo;effectful operation&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://www.codessl.com/about/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 21:49:35 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.codessl.com/about/</guid><description>About codessl.com I blog about software development, functional programming and machine learning.
If it is not obvious already, ssl is my initial.
About Sheng-Loong Su I am currently working as a Senior Software Engineer at a startup, Smartpay. As part of the founding team, I enjoy building products and services using pure functional programming with Scala and the Typelevel stack (Cats, Cats Effect, fs2, http4s, etc.</description></item></channel></rss>